Oh my goodness.
‫عجبًا.‬
It's all right now.
‫لا تقلق.‬
It won't happen again.
‫لن يتكرر ما حدث.‬
Never again will blood be shed in these woods.
‫لن تُسفك الدماء في هذه الغابة مجددًا.‬
Isn't that right?
‫أليس كذلك؟‬
CHILDREN CONTINUE TO FALL TO THEIR DEATH BY ACCIDENT OR SUICIDE?
‫"هل سيستمر الأطفال في الموت‬ ‫إثر حادث أو بالانتحار؟"‬
ARE THEY PLAYING DANGEROUS GAMES? ANOTHER CHILD DEAD!
‫"هل يلعبون ألعابًا خطرة؟‬ ‫يلقى طفل آخر حتفه!"‬
FIFTH VICTIM! ROOFTOP TRESPASSING RESTRICTIONS TO BE STRENGTHENED
‫الضحية الخامسة!‬ ‫التشديد على منع انتهاك حرمة الأسطح"‬
RALPH LUDWICH MEMORIAL HOSPITAL
‫"مستشفى (رالف لودفيتش) التذكارية"‬
You don't remember a thing?
‫ألا تتذكّر شيئًا؟‬
Do you remember what you were doing on the roof?
‫ألا تتذكّر ما كنت تفعله على سطح المبنى؟‬
Anything you can tell me would be helpful.
‫قد تفيدنا أي معلومة تقولها.‬
Tell him, Martin.
‫أخبره يا "مارتن".‬
If you hadn't hit the first-floor eaves and landed on that branch,
‫لولا اصطدامك بحافة الطابق الأول‬ ‫وسقوطك على فرع الشجرة،‬
you could've died!
‫لكنت مت!‬
Talk to the doctor!
‫تحدّث إلى الطبيب!‬
You have to stop doing these idiotic things!
‫يجب أن تكفّ عن اقتراف تلك الحماقات.‬
Now, now, ma'am.
‫حسبك يا سيدتي.‬
But if my boy had died… I don't know what I would've done.
‫لا أعرف ما كنت قد أفعل إن مات ابني.‬
It's all right, ma'am.
‫لا عليك يا سيدتي.‬
I am here to give your son the counseling he needs.
‫أتيت لأمنح ابنك ما يلزمه من استشارة.‬
I know, I realize that. It's just that…
‫أعرف، أدرك ذلك. الأمر وما فيه…‬
Look, let's talk outside, okay?
‫لنتحدث في الخارج، اتفقنا؟‬
Dieter, be a good boy and stay there.
‫"ديتر"، كن مطيعًا وابق هنا.‬
And don't go into that room.
‫ولا تدخل تلك الغرفة.‬
Is that your grandson, doctor?
‫هل هو حفيدك يا دكتور؟‬
No, I'm just looking after him for a while.
‫لا، أنا أعتني به لفترة.‬
Hi.
‫مرحبًا.‬
My name is Dieter.
‫اسمي "ديتر".‬
I'm Martin.
‫أنا "مارتن".‬
Does it hurt?
‫أتؤلمك؟‬
Does what hurt?
‫ما التي تؤلمني؟‬
Those wounds that are all wrapped up.
‫تلك الجروح المضمدة.‬
You must've been scared when you fell off that roof, right?
‫من المؤكد أنك خفت عند السقوط من على السطح.‬
You can't do that! What are you doing?
‫لا يمكنك فعل هذا! ما الذي تفعله؟‬
My shoes are in that bag. Go get them.
‫حذائي في تلك الحقيبة. أحضره.‬
Are you kidding? You have to lie down!
‫هل تمزح؟ يجب أن تستلقي!‬
Get my dang shoes.
‫أحضر حذائي اللعين.‬
Where are you going?
‫إلى أين تذهب؟‬
You'll get yelled at.
‫ستُوبّخ.‬
So, what if I do get yelled at?
‫وإن يكن؟‬
I'm not scared of getting yelled at.
‫لست خائفًا من التوبيخ.‬
It's just like he said.
‫الأمر كما وصفه بالضبط.‬
"If you survive, go outside. The world will be different."
‫"إن نجوت، فاخرج وستجد الحياة مختلفة."‬
The world isn't any different. I'm the one who has changed.
‫لم تتغيّر الحياة. بل أنا من تغيّرت.‬
You see, I'm one of the chosen.
‫أنا من المُختارين.‬
I'm bored.
‫أشعر بالضجر.‬
I never realized how boring the world is.
‫لم أدرك قط كم أن الحياة مضجرة.‬
Hey! Watch out!
‫مهلًا! انتبه!‬
Follow me. There is nothing to be afraid of.
‫اتبعني. ما من شيء يستدعي الخوف.‬
Why did you do that?
‫لمَ فعلت ذلك؟‬
Look at how scared he is.
‫تأمل مدى خوفه.‬
Cut that out!
‫كفى!‬
I told you, look at him!
‫قلت لك، تأمله!‬
"I don't want to die! Help me!"
‫"لا أريد أن أموت! ساعدني!"‬
You're in luck.
‫أنت محظوظ.‬
I'll let you live.
‫سأدعك تعيش.‬
Let me answer your question from earlier.
‫سأجيبك عن سؤالك الذي طرحته سابقًا.‬
You asked me if I was scared when I fell off the roof, right?
‫سألتني عمّا إن خفت عند السقوط من على السطح.‬
Yeah.
‫أجل.‬
Of course, I was not scared.
‫لم أخف طبعًا.‬
I was just playing a game.
‫كنت ألعب لعبة.‬
A game?
‫لعبة؟‬
But a bunch of kids have died from it!
‫لكن مات عدد من الأطفال بسببها!‬
It's a lot of fun.
‫إنها ممتعة للغاية.‬
It's a game, after all.
‫إنها مجرد لعبة.‬
We stand facing one another at the edge of the roof of an abandoned building.
‫نقف في مواجهة بعضنا البعض‬ ‫على حافة سطح مبنى مهجور.‬
Then we close our eyes and walk toward each other one step at a time.
‫ثم نغمض عينينا‬ ‫ونتخذ خطوة باتجاه بعضنا البعض في كل مرة.‬
It's a duel.
‫إنها مبارزة.‬
It doesn't matter if you fall or not. If you survive, you win.
‫لا يهم إن سقطت أم لا، إذ من ينجو يفوز.‬
Why do you do that?
‫لم تفعل ذلك؟‬
We are testing fate.
‫نختبر قدرنا.‬
Whoever survives is a chosen one.
‫من ينجو يكون المُختار.‬
Don't you understand what I'm saying?
‫ألا تفهم كلامي؟‬
Whoever survives can play the game again another day.
‫يمكن لمن ينجو‬ ‫أن يلعب اللعبة مجددًا في يوم آخر.‬
"Game?" Do you call that a game?
‫"لعبة"؟ أتعتبر هذه لعبة؟‬
We do it because the world is so boring.
‫نلعبها لأن العالم مضجر.‬
It's a load of fun.
‫إنها ممتعة للغاية.‬
Only the chosen ones can continue to play the game.
‫وحدهم المختارون يمكنهم الاستمرار باللعب.‬
Don't you get it?
‫ألا تفهم؟‬
I thought you were one of us.
‫حسبتك أحدنا.‬
Come with me.
‫تعال معي.‬
If you don't understand after seeing it, then you really are stupid.
‫إن لم تفهم بعدما تراها،‬ ‫فستكون شديد الغباء.‬
Hey! You don't mean to go to the roof, do you?
‫مهلًا! أتنوي الصعود إلى السطح؟‬
Only the chosen, the gifted ones survive. Just like him.
‫المُختارون فقط والموهوبون هم من ينجون.‬ ‫من هم مثله.‬
Like who?
‫مثل من؟‬
The guy who taught us this game.
‫الرجل الذي علّمنا هذه اللعبة.‬
Who is he?
‫من هو؟‬
He is a friend of us, gifted kids.
‫إنه صديقنا، نحن الفتية الموهوبون.‬
Come on. Hurry up!
‫هيا. أسرع!‬
I don't want to.
‫لا أريد.‬
Just come with me!
‫تعال معي!‬
Let go of me!
‫اتركني!‬
I know you'll understand, so just come!
‫أنا متيقن من أنك ستفهم، فتعال!‬
Stop that!
‫توقف!‬
Who gave you those bruises?
‫من أصابك بتلك الكدمات؟‬
Your parents?
‫والداك؟‬
Do you still want to go back to them after what they did?
‫أما زلت تريد العودة إليهما بعد ما فعلاه؟‬
Do you still want to be part of this stupid world after what they did to you?
‫هل ما زلت تريد أن تكون جزءًا‬ ‫من هذا العالم الغبي بعد الذي ألحقاه بك؟‬
Come on! you gotta see this!
‫هيا! يجب أن ترى هذا!‬
So, how do you like the view?
‫إذًا، ما رأيك بهذا المنظر؟‬
How does it feel?
‫بم يشعرك؟‬
Stand up.
‫انهض.‬
What are you afraid of?
‫مم أنت خائف؟‬
Stand up, close your eyes, and walk.
‫قف، أغمض عينيك وامش.‬
Stand up.
‫انهض.‬
I get it now.
‫فهمت الآن.‬
I understand what you've been saying.
‫أفهم ما كنت تقوله.‬
I once thought the world was full of darkness.
‫سبق أن تصوّرت العالم تسوده الظلمات.‬
I thought the future was dark too.
‫تصوّرت أيضًا أن قتامة المستقبل تفوق التحمّل.‬
What's your favorite food?
‫ما هو طعامك المفضل؟‬
The other day, I had some really good sausages!
‫تناولت في يوم سابق نقانق شهية للغاية!‬
But if I die, I'll never be able to eat them again!
‫لكن إن مت، فلن أتمكن من أكلها مجددًا!‬
You coward.
‫جبان.‬
I like soccer! But if I die, I'll never be able to play it again!
‫أحب كرة القدم!‬ ‫لكن إن مت، فلن أتمكن من أن ألعبها مجددًا!‬
Weakling.
‫ضعيف.‬
I like Dr. Reichwein!
‫أحب الدكتور "رايشفاين"!‬
His secretary, Meredith, is nice too!
‫سكرتيرته "ميريديث" لطيفة أيضًا!‬
But if I die, I'll never see them again!
‫لكنني إن متّ فلن أراهما مجددًا!‬
There are always things to be scared of.
‫ثمة ما نخافه دائمًا.‬
He said dealing with them is how we grow up.
‫قال إن التعامل مع مخاوفنا‬ ‫هو ما يساهم في نمونا.‬
Tenma taught me that the future will be better!
‫علّمني "تينما" أن المستقبل سيكون أفضل!‬
If I die…
‫إن مت‬
If I die, I'll never see Tenma again.
‫فلن أرى "تينما" مجددًا.‬
I'm scared!
‫أنا خائف!‬
Don't panic. Kneel slowly.
‫لا تهلع. اجث على ركبتيك ببطء.‬
I'll never be like him.
‫لن أصبح مثله أبدًا.‬
I'll never be like Johan.
‫لن أصبح مثل "يوهان" أبدًا.‬
"Johan?"
‫"يوهان"؟‬
Johan is playing an even bigger game.
‫بل يلعب "يوهان" لعبًا أكبر.‬
He said he'll be killed soon.
‫قال إنه سيُقتل قريبًا.‬
He said a Japanese man was going to shoot and kill him soon.
‫قال إن ثمة رجلًا يابانيًا‬ ‫سيطلق النار عليه ويقتله قريبًا.‬
I closed my eyes and walked along the edge of the roof.
‫أغمضت عينيّ وسرت على حافة السطح.‬
It's the truth. I really did it.
‫إنها الحقيقة. هذا ما فعلته حقًا.‬
I was not afraid at all.
‫لم أخف على الإطلاق.‬
Joachim was supposed to be walking towards me, but when I opened my eyes,
‫كان يُفترض بـ"يواكيم" أن يسير نحوي،‬ ‫لكن عندما فتحت عينيّ،‬
he was gone.
‫كان قد اختفى.‬
I saw it! I saw him the moment he died!
‫رأيت ما حدث! رأيته لحظة وفاته!‬
People do die.
‫يموت الناس.‬
I brought some tea.
‫أحضرت الشاي.‬
Thank you.
‫شكرًا.‬
What's wrong with my boy?
‫ما خطب ولدي؟‬
He doesn't seem to understand just what he has done.
‫يبدو أنه لا يدرك ما فعله.‬
Thank goodness he survived,
‫الحمد لله أنه نجا،‬
but I feel so awful for poor dead Joachim's parents.
‫لكنني أشعر بالسوء‬ ‫تجاه والديّ "يواكيم" المسكين.‬
Please talk some sense into him.
‫أقنعه من فضلك.‬
He seems to be listening to you.
‫يبدو أنه ينصت إليك.‬
She gets on my case like that every day.
‫تنتقدني هكذا يوميًا.‬
She doesn't understand a thing.
‫إنها لا تفهم شيئًا.‬
She won't let me out of the house. I can't even watch TV or read comics.
‫لن تسمح لي بالخروج من البيت. أُمنع حتى‬ ‫من مشاهدة التلفاز أو قراءة القصص المصوّرة.‬
You must be bored.
‫لا بد أنك ضجرت.‬
I'll bring you something to do.
‫سأمنحك ما تفعله.‬
Really? You will?
‫حقًا؟ ستفعل؟‬
You can't read comics, but picture books should be fine.
‫أنت ممنوع من قراءة القصص المصوّرة‬ ‫ولكن الكتب المصوّرة لا بأس بها.‬
What? A picture book? That just sounds plain dumb.
‫ماذا؟ كتب مصوّرة؟ ما أغباها من فكرة.‬
Hey! What about that crazy game you told us about the other day?
‫ماذا عن اللعبة الجنونية‬ ‫التي أخبرتنا عنها سابقًا؟‬
You said you were about to be shot and killed, right?
‫قلت إنك على وشك التعرّض لإطلاق النار، صحيح؟‬
That sounds so exciting!
‫هذه تجربة مثيرة للغاية!‬
So, when is that Japanese guy going to shoot you? Tell me, Johan.
‫إذًا، متى سيطلق ذلك الياباني النار عليك؟‬ ‫أخبرني يا "يوهان".‬
The first edition of Hermann Hesse's Steppenwolf.
‫النسخة الأولى‬ ‫من كتاب "هيرمان هيس"، "ستبنولف".‬
And this is the first edition of Hoffmann's Night Pieces.
‫وهذه هي النسخة الأولى‬ ‫من قصة "هوفمان"، "قطع الليل".‬
And here is a complete collection of Goethe's poetry.
‫وهذه هي المجموعة الكاملة من شعر "غوته".‬
Goodness me! Even for me,
‫يا للجمال! حتى بالنسبة إليّ،‬
the head librarian at Munich University's Fredrich Emmanuel Library,
‫كبير أمناء مكتبة "فريدريك إيمانويل"‬ ‫في جامعة "ميونخ"،‬
this collection of books is dazzling.
‫فقد أبهرتني مجموعة الكتب هذه.‬
Though I am a self-taught man who never went to university,
‫مع أنني رجل عصامي لم يلتحق بالجامعة،‬
I only got this far by reading every book I could lay my hands on.
‫إلا أن ما وصلت إليه‬ ‫حققته بقراءة كل كتاب قد حظيت به.‬
I am so grateful you decided to donate this amazing collection to our library.
‫أنا ممتن جدًا‬ ‫لتبرعك بهذه المجموعة المذهلة لمكتبتنا.‬
I don't have words to express my appreciation.
‫ما من كلام يسعفني للتعبير عن مدى امتناني.‬
My vision is failing me so I can no longer even read.
‫يخذلني بصري وما عدت قادرًا على القراءة.‬
They should be available
‫يجب أن تكون متاحة‬
to the university's students rather than sitting here in my study.
‫لطلاب الجامعة عوضًا عن إبقائها في مكتبي.‬
Agreed. There are several precious volumes here,
‫أتفق معك. ثمة مجلدات قيّمة هنا،‬
but we would like them to be available to the public too.
‫لكننا نود أن نتيحها للعامة أيضًا.‬
That reminds me. We've already decided where they will be kept.
‫ذكّرني ذلك‬ ‫بأننا توصلنا إلى المكان الذي سنضعها فيه.‬
We would also like to hold a ceremony,
‫نود أيضًا أن نقيم احتفالًا،‬
so would it be possible for you to come to our library?
‫فهل من الممكن أن تأتي إلى مكتبتنا؟‬
-What about security? -Huh?
‫- ماذا عن الإجراءات الأمنية؟‬ ‫- ماذا؟‬
Now that Mr. Schuwald is appearing in public more often,
‫بما أن السيد "شوفالد" بات يظهر‬ ‫في الأماكن العامة أكثر من ذي قبل‬
we've had to keep an eye on some dangerous people.
‫فإن علينا حمايته‬ ‫من بعض من يمثلون خطرًا عليه.‬
Make sure the guests are properly vetted.
‫احرص على التحرّي عن الضيوف بدقة.‬
Isn't that right, Johan?
‫ألست محقًا يا سيد "يوهان"؟‬
Yes.
‫نعم.‬
Since it was Johan and Karl's idea to donate this collection,
‫بما أن "يوهان" و"كارل"‬ ‫من اقترحا فكرة التبرع بهذه المجموعة،‬
they'll be the ones to arrange things at the library.
‫فهما من سيتوليان الترتيبات‬ ‫المرتبطة بالمكتبة.‬
I'm Gerhmann, the head librarian.
‫أنا "غيرمان"، كبير أمناء المكتبة.‬
It's nice to meet you.
‫سررت بلقائك.‬
Nice to meet you.
‫سعدت بلقائك.‬
MUNICH UNIVERSITY LIBRARY
‫"مكتبة جامعة (ميونخ)"‬
This is the room that will hold Mr. Schuwald's collection.
‫هذه هي الغرفة‬ ‫التي ستضم مجموعة السيد "شوفالد".‬
It's off-limits to the public.
‫يُمنع العامة من دخولها.‬
I'm sure you've never been here.
‫أنا متأكد من أنكما لم تدخلاها من قبل.‬
Besides having the optimum temperature and humidity for storing books,
‫إلى جانب ضبط درجة الحرارة والرطوبة‬ ‫على أمثل درجة لحفظ الكتب،‬
it's also protected against theft and fire.
‫فإن الغرفة محصنة أيضًا من السرقة والإحراق.‬
What a large number of books.
‫يا له من عدد كبير من الكتب.‬
A real testament to mankind, Johan.
‫إنها تركة حقيقية للبشرية يا "يوهان".‬
Yes, a testament to mankind.
‫أجل، تركة للبشرية.‬
The ceremony celebrating the donation will be held here in Central Hall.
‫ستُقام مراسم الاحتفال بالتبرع‬ ‫هنا في القاعة المركزية.‬
As Mr. Schuwald's assistant has requested, security will be tight.
‫كما طلب مساعد السيد "شوفالد"،‬ ‫فإن الإجراءات الأمنية ستكون مشددة.‬
We want Mr. Schuwald to feel at ease here.
‫نريد أن يشعر السيد "شوفالد" بالراحة هنا.‬
Good.
‫جيد.‬
I'm sure my father will be glad to attend.
‫أنا متأكد من أن والدي‬ ‫سيسعد بحضور الاحتفال.‬
Right, Johan?
‫أليس كذلك يا "يوهان"؟‬
What's wrong, Johan?
‫ما الخطب يا "يوهان"؟‬
Excuse me for a moment.
‫اعذرني للحظة.‬
Can I help you find something?
‫هل لي أن أساعدك في العثور على كتاب؟‬
Yes.
‫نعم.‬
I'm looking for a nice picture book for a friend of mine.
‫أبحث عن كتاب مصوّر ممتع لصديق لي.‬
For a friend?
‫لصديق؟‬
Yes.
‫نعم.‬
A friend.
‫صديق.‬
Let me see.
‫دعني أرى.‬
How about this one?
‫ما رأيك في هذا الكتاب؟‬
Aren't those drawings lovely?
‫أليست رسومات جميلة؟‬
But a little too grown-up.
‫لكنها أكبر من سنه.‬
Your friend isn't an adult?
‫أليس شخصًا راشدًا؟‬
Well then, how about this one?
‫حسنًا إذًا، ما رأيك في هذا؟‬
Oh, dear me!
‫ويلاه!‬
Thank you, you're so kind.
‫أشكرك. ما ألطفك.‬
I'm such a klutz. This always happens to me.
‫أنا خرقاء. دائمًا ما يحدث هذا معي.‬
Oh, here's what I was looking for.
‫هذا ما كنت أبحث عنه.‬
This is the book I recommend.
‫هذا هو الكتاب الذي أوصي به.‬
Do you like that one?
‫أيعجبك؟‬
My! What nice drawings.
‫عجبًا! ما أجملها من رسومات.‬
I wonder who this is by. Excuse me for a moment.
‫من مؤلّفه يا ترى؟ من بعد إذنك.‬
"Emil Scherbe. Moravia Publishing."
‫"إميل شيربه"، دار "مورافيا" للنشر.‬
That's a Czech publisher in Prague.
‫إنها دار نشر تشيكية في "براغ".‬
The Czech Republic has a lot of great picture book authors.
‫لدى جمهورية "التشيك"‬ ‫الكثير من مؤلفي الكتب المصوّرة الرائعين.‬
But I've never heard of the author Scherbe.
‫لكنني لم أسمع قط بالمؤلف "شيربه".‬
He must not be very famous.
‫لا بد أنه كاتب مغمور.‬
Is there something wrong?
‫أمن خطب ما؟‬
Help!
‫النجدة!‬
Someone, help!
‫فليساعدني أحد!‬
Dang, it sure is hot this summer.
‫اللعنة، يا له من صيف حار.‬
It's just awful.
‫كم هذا فظيع.‬
ANNOUNCEMENT: HANS GEORG SCHUWALD BOOK DONATION CEREMONY
‫"إعلان، حفل (هانس جورج شوفالد)‬ ‫للتبرع بالكتب"‬
WITH SPEECH BY MR. SCHUWALD
‫"سيقلي فيه السيد (شوفالد) خطابًا"‬
This is the place.
‫هذا هو المكان المناسب.‬
This is where I'll shoot him from.
‫سأطلق النار عليه من هنا.‬